so going back to our many core
challenges we have seen that when the
number of cores grows
so does the coherence traffic on the
chip
and for that we needed a scalable
on-chip network such as a mesh
and the directory coherence which we
have already seen in our cache coherence
lesson
another thing
that having more cores
will make more difficult is that as the
number of cores goes up
the off-chip traffic that we need goes
up to have decent performance
we will as we increase the number of
cores increase the number of on-chip
caches so if we have four cores we have
four level one and possibly level 2
caches when we have 64 cores we'll have
64 level 1 and level 2 caches
so each
core
doesn't really generate more misses but
it generates the same number of misses
regardless of how many cores we have so
we have the same number of misses per
core so as we have more cores the number
of memory requests
which is what we do when we have a miss
would go up in proportion to the number
of cores
now note that the number of pins the
number of those little wires sticking
out of a chip
does go up slowly
but not in proportion or anywhere close
to in proportion to the number of cores
so if we double the number of cores
possibly we get maybe 10 percent more
pins but that's it
because these pins have to physically be
large enough to not break when we are
moving the chip around
and plugging it into a motherboard so
what happens is we get some little
improvement in off-chip throughput while
our demand for it basically grows in
proportion to the number of cores so our
off-chip available throughput becomes a
bottleneck so we need to reduce the
number of memory requests that we
generate per core and the way we do that
is to make the last level cache which in
most today's processors is the level
three cache
shared so that all cores go to that
cache and its size is shared equally by
all the cores and the size of that cache
needs to go up in proportion to the
number of cores as it goes up so as we
double the number of cores we should at
least double the size of the last level
cache but there is a problem to having
one huge llc like this
such a large cache would be slow and if
it's really one single cache it would
have one entry point where we enter the
address and expect the data out
and that entry point needs to be
somewhere on our chip that now possibly
has a mesh or another advanced network
and that means that that one point
will be where we send all of the level
two misses so it would become a
bottleneck pretty much now we don't get
to use all of the links equally this set
of links that go to this entry point for
the cache would get much more traffic
than the other links if we double the
number of cores then those links around
the entry point get double the traffic
so what we do
is we don't have just one big last level
cache we have what is called a
distributed last level cache now let's
see what that looks like